Cutting Gordian Knots: Salvaging Misfolded Proteins

Misfolded proteins are increasingly recognized as the root cause of a wide array of human diseases. Clearly, mutations in the primary amino acid sequence can cause loss of enzyme, or of structural function, as catalytic sites or motifs for protein-protein interactions are disrupted; in some cases, misfolded proteins are recognized as defective and even degraded through endoplasmic reticulum (ER) or ubiquitin-proteasome pathways. Cystic fibrosis, Marfan syndrome, Fabry disease, muscular dystrophy, and retinitis pigmentosa all fall into this general category; misfolded tumor suppressor gene products such as p53 can even contribute to malignancy. In other cases, misfolded proteins cause pathology by accumulating. Excessive intracellular accretion can trigger ER stress responses that culminate in apoptotic suicide; diseases in this group include α1-antitrypsin deficiency, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, Huntington disease, and diabetes. Conversely, excess misfolded extracellular proteins can cause cell death or dysfunction through the formation of amyloid aggregates, as in Alzheimer disease and Creutzfeld-Jakob spongiform encephalopathy (prion disease).

Gaucher disease (GD) is the most common of the lysosomal storage disorders; it also is an excellent candidate for therapeutic approaches that influence protein folding. GD results from a variety of recessive genetic mutations (more than 150!) leading to misfolded β-gluocerebrosidase enzymes that are either inactive or are prematurely degraded in the ER. In most cell types, low-level residual enzyme activity is sufficient to prevent cellular dysfunction. Cells responsible for catabolizing large amounts of glucocerebroside, however, are overwhelmed. Consequently, macrophages progressively accumulate nondegraded glucosylceramide from the membranes of senescent leukocytes and red cells. Besides causing organomegaly, the macrophages also are activated by their glycolipid burden, elaborating pro-inflammatory cytokines. Thus, GD causes bone destruction, thrombocytopenia due to hypersplenism, and central nervous system (CNS) dysfunction attributed to microglial cell cytokine production. Worse, in type II disease, a complete absence of enzyme activity leads to infantile neuronal dysfunction and death consequent to the inability to recycle critical membrane constituents.

The treatment option currently in widest use is somewhat less than ideal. Enzyme replacement therapy (ERT), using recombinant enzymes, takes advantage of the fact that terminal mannose-6-phosphate glycosylation of glucocerebrosidase allows the protein to be bound to surface mannose receptors, endocytosed, and specifically targeted to the lysosomal compartment. Because defective macrophages are the central pathologic problem, ERT restores enzyme activity precisely to where it needs to go. Unfortunately, this therapy is extremely expensive ($300,000 annually) and requires regular intravenous administration, and the enzymes do not cross the blood-brain barrier for treating CNS deficiency.

To the rescue comes the class of pharmacologic chaperones, small molecules that stabilize or reactivate improperly folded glucocerebrosidase. Studies show that if only 10% of normal enzyme activity can be restored, the vast majority of GD-associated pathologic effects can be ameliorated. These agents (isofagomine, N-octyl-β-valienamine) are orally available and inexpensive and cross the blood-brain barrier, making them potentially valuable in therapy for all forms of GD. If the molecular chaperones become as successful as their advance press suggests, regimens based on such agents also may become therapeutic paradigms for the treatment of other lysosomal storage disorders—as well as the myriad illnesses (such as cystic fibrosis) that result from defective protein folding.

Aspirin: An Old Actor with a New Role

Rubor (erythema), tumor (swelling), calor (warmth), and dolor (pain) have long been recognized as classic elements of inflammation. These are active features driven by a host of mediators that affect the behavior of blood vessels, inflammatory cells, and nerves. In particular, metabolites of arachidonic acid such as the prostaglandins and leukotrienes play important roles. Consequently, drugs that target the phospholipase-mediated release of arachidonic acid precursors (e.g., glucocorticoids) or the production of prostaglandins (e.g., cyclooxygenase [COX] inhibitors, such as aspirin) have a salubrious effect on inflammation. These drugs, however, are not without side effects.

Fortunately, several new targets are in the therapeutic cross-hairs thanks to an improved understanding of the normal pathways by which inflammation is intrinsically modulated.

• Until recently, the natural resolution of inflammation was considered a passive process; the prevailing view was that once the inciting stimulus was removed by the inflammatory response, the signals driving the activity just progressively “fizzled out.” It is now clear, however, that the pathways triggered early in inflammation also set into motion the production of mediators that ultimately actively shut down inflammation. Thus, arachidonate precursors that can give rise to pro-inflammatory leukotrienes—via the action of 5-lipoxygenase—also can be converted to anti-inflammatory lipoxins through the subsequent activity of 12-lipoxygenase. Somewhat counterintuitively, then, upstream inhibition of the 5-lipoxygenase enzyme can actually prolong and augment inflammation by removing the substrate for a later enzyme that actively promotes resolution.
• Still other natural anti-inflammatory compounds—called resolvins and protectins—are generated from omega-3 fatty acids such as eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA). Found in superabundance in cold-water fish, these essential polyunsaturated fatty acids have long been associated with beneficial effects in atherosclerosis, asthma, and cancer. When EPA and DHA are sequentially modified by cytochrome P-450 and lipoxygenase enzymes, they form potent anti-inflammatory products that block neutrophil and monocyte recruitment and mediator production. A number of the resolvins also are impressively analgesic, interfering with both peripheral and central pain pathways. Consequently, several resolvin analogues are in clinical trials; although they show clinical promise, their availability is several years away.

Fortuitously, aspirin, an over-the-counter drug that augments resolvin production, is already on hand. The well-described mechanism of action for aspirin is the irreversible acetylation of COX proteins. Although this prevents the production of the pro-inflammatory prostaglandins, the acetylated protein can be the first enzymatic step in producing resolvins! Thus, aspirin is not only anti-inflammatory but also pro-resolving; the other NSAIDs, which merely block (but do not acetylate) COX, do not have this effect. It is more than ironic that one of the oldest (and cheapest) of drugs may be at the cutting edge of the future of anti-inflammatory agents.

Shooting for PAR: Hitting a Hole-in-One…or a Bogey?

Platelet activation and aggregation play an important role in thrombogenesis, as well as atherogenesis. Thus, platelet activation is a critical component of the pathogenesis of diseases such as myocardial infarction and cerebrovascular stroke. Based on the central importance of platelets, the current standard of preventive care for patients with a previous history of atherothrombotic diseases involves a two-pronged antiplatelet approach:

• Aspirin blocks platelet thromboxane A2 (TxA2) synthesis by irreversibly inhibiting cyclooxygenase. TxA2 is a potent mediator of platelet aggregation. Although endothelial cyclooxygenase is likewise inhibited by aspirin—with resulting loss of prostacyclin (i.e., prostaglandin I2 [PGI2]) synthesis—the effect on the antithrombotic PGI2 production is transient, because endothelial cells continuously synthesize new cyclooxygenase.
• Thienopyridine (e.g., clopidogrel) blockade of platelet adenosine diphosphate (ADP) receptors (also called P2Y12). Because ADP also is a major trigger for platelet activation and aggregation, receptor blockade has been shown to be a potent adjunct for preventing recurrent atherothrombosis.

Combined blockade of TxA2 and ADP has well-documented benefits in reducing the risk of recurrent infarction or stroke. This strategy, however, leaves completely unimpeded the activation of platelets by thrombin—probably the most potent pathway that can promote platelet aggregation. Thrombin-mediated activation constitutes an important reason why patients on aspirin and thienopyridines can nevertheless experience recurrent thrombotic events.

Besides generating fibrin from fibrinogen, thrombin activates platelets via the PAR-1 and PAR-4 protease-activated receptors (PARs) that are cleaved by proteases to make a tethered ligand that can efficiently stimulate the digested receptor. Although other PARs can participate in inflammation and pain pathways, PAR-1 is the major thrombin receptor on platelets; hence, it causes prompt and profound platelet activation.

Thus, PAR-1–specific blockade (e.g., with vorapaxar) significantly reduces recurrent atherothrombotic events such as myocardial infarction—even in patients already receiving aspirin and clopidogrel. Fortunately, PAR-1 blockade does not affect the normal coagulation cascade involving thrombin. As might also be anticipated, however, such PAR-1 antagonism is associated with an increased risk of bleeding, including cerebral hemorrhage. Consequently, although going for PAR might seem like a clear winner, this approach will need to be carefully evaluated for individual patients in light of some of the potential (hemorrhagic) traps.

Yet another mechanism of platelet aggregation is cross-linking through their cell surface glycoprotein IIb/IIIa receptors by fibrinogen. Accordingly, antagonists (e.g., abciximab, eptifibatide, tirofiban) of these glycoprotein receptors also can be used as powerful antiplatelet agents. These agents can be administered only intravenously, however, so they typically are used for selected clinical indications in the hospital setting (e.g., to prevent acute vascular stent thrombosis), and not for widespread outpatient atherothrombosis prevention.

Amyloid: Breaking Up Is Hard to Do

Approximately 15 biochemically distinct proteins have the capacity to fold into relatively insoluble β-pleated sheets to produce morphologically identical-looking amyloid fibrils. There are three major forms of amyloid: AL (immunoglobulin light chains), AA (a protein derived from SAA, an acute-phase reactant made in the liver), and Aβ amyloid, found in the cerebral plaques of Alzheimer disease. All forms are associated with a glycoprotein (the P component) that is essential for fibril deposition. Some of these unfolded molecules are directly toxic; thus, immunoglobulin light chains in myeloma bring myocardial cells to a standstill, and the Aβ amyloid in Alzheimer disease plaques is noxious for neurons. The fibrils in all forms get progressively cross-linked, thereby becoming resistant to degradation. The amyloid thus formed progressively accumulates like so much extracellular linoleum, eventually squeezing out normal parenchyma. Typically, the prognosis for patients affected by amyloid has been exceptionally grim; a diagnosis of cardiac involvement usually translates to death within 1 to 2 years.

In all of these entities, the protein aggregation has long been presumed to be relentless and irreversible; at the very best, clinicians could only hope to prevent further accumulation. Accordingly, the traditional approaches to therapy focus on treating the underlying disease—specifically, chemotherapy for myeloma (with AL amyloidosis) and antibiotics for chronic infections or anti- inflammatory agents for autoimmune diseases (with AA amyloidosis).

Some breakthroughs appear imminent, however: Building on an improved understanding of protein folding, research has led to production of a number of useful small molecules—so-called “amyloid breakers,” now entering into clinical trial. Some of these interfere with the binding of chaperone proteins such as substance P and apolipoprotein E4 (apoE4), which can propagate the β-sheet content of Aβ peptides and promote pathogenic fibril formation in the brain: CPHPC is a carboxypyrrolidinyl carboxylic acid derivative that binds to the P component and results in its prompt removal from the circulation thus eliminating an important “nucleation factor” for amyloid propagation. Other agents such as tramiprosate inhibit the interactions between interstitial glycosaminoglycans and Aβ that normally stabilize fibril formation; these breakers are sulfated glycosaminoglycan mimetics. Yet another approach is to stabilize native transthyretin tetramers with drugs like tafamadis or diflunisal to prevent the dissociation of monomeric components (e.g., from mutant isoforms) that can then misfold into amyloid fibrils.

With these approaches, coupled with earlier detection of amyloid deposits before irreversible damage is done, what previously has been an intractable and inexorable process may eventually become manageable.

Extracorporeal Photopheresis: Seeing the Light on Graft-versus-Host Disease

Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation after radiochemotherapy is an important treatment modality for certain leukemias and lymphomas, and graft-versus-tumor effect underlies some of its therapeutic efficacy. Unfortunately, allogeneic transplantation also carries a significant—and potentially life-threatening—risk of graft-versus-host-disease (GVHD). Thus, donor lymphocytes have the capacity to attack a variety of host tissues, leading to intractable diarrhea, pulmonary fibrosis, cutaneous inflammation, hepatobiliary disease, and/or musculoskeletal injury.

Older approaches to control or prevent GVHD include the following:

• Precise DNA sequence–based donor and host human leukocyte antigen (HLA) matching. Except for transplantation between identical twins, however, mismatch of minor HLA antigens is inevitable, even with sibling transplants.
• Autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. This modality is not favored currently because graft-versus-tumor effect is lost.
• Depletion of donor T cells with monoclonal antibodies to CD3 or other T cell markers. Unfortunately, this leads to a reduced graft-versus-tumor effect, poorer overall marrow engraftment, and much more frequent development of Epstein-Barr virus (EBV)-associated B cell tumors, which can be fatal.
• Administration of immunosuppressive drugs. Such regimens constitute a mainstay of current efforts to control GVHD but carry the usual downside of opportunistic infections and EBV-related malignancies.

When these strategies fail, transplant physicians are increasingly turning to the light—that is, to the use of extracorporeal photopheresis (ECP) to treat white blood cells outside of the body and then return them to the host.

ECP uses 8-methoxypsoralen (8MP), a plant compound that when activated by sunlight cross-links DNA to cause apoptosis of cells. Psoralens have been used since the time of the Pharaohs for a variety of dermatologic conditions; they are the “P” in PUVA (psoralen plus ultraviolet A [UV-A] light) therapy for psoriasis. In ECP, a continuous centrifugal apheresis of blood allows white cells to be separated and externally treated with low doses of 8MP and visible-wavelength light; these are then returned to the patient during the same pheresis session. The ECP approach appears to work not so much by killing proliferating lymphocytes (as had been thought originally) but by generation of regulatory T cells. This may occur by dendritic cell–mediated processing and presentation of the activated and apoptotic cells. The effect is remarkably antigen-specific—there is generally only suppression of the GVHD-causing clones and not a global immunosuppression. The same approach also is effective in treating cutaneous T cell lymphomas and for preventing rejection in solid organ transplants; clinicians are even beginning to see the ECP light for some autoimmune disorders such as Crohn disease and scleroderma!

Managing Marfan: It’s Just Another (TGF)-βrick in the Wall

Marfan syndrome is an autosomal dominant disorder caused by mutations in the FBN1 gene that lead to defective synthesis of fibrillin, a major glycoprotein constituent of connective tissues. As a consequence, affected patients have a number of defects throughout the body, including joint laxity, increased growth of appendageal bones, and lens subluxation. The clinically most important manifestation of Marfan’s, however, is a propensity for aortic aneurysm formation, secondary to defective matrix synthesis in the aortic media. The markedly diminished wall integrity contributes to mortality through acute spontaneous aortic dissections.

Although fibrillin originally was thought to be only a scaffolding protein that provided a passive framework for matrix synthesis, it turns out to be critical for the sequestration of transforming growth factor-β (TGF-β), an important signaling molecule that regulates smooth muscle and fibroblast growth and synthetic repertoires. Too little fibrillin in the matrix means that too much free TGF-β is available to interact with its receptor (TGF-βR) on medial mesenchymal cells. As a result, the normally elastic aortic wall is replaced by structurally weak glycosaminoglycans and other connective elements that cannot withstand the rigors of pulsatile systolic pressures. With time, pathologic vascular wall remodeling leads to formation of aneurysms that are at risk for catastrophic ruptures.

In view of these specific mechanisms, TGF-βR blockade has become an attractive target. Additionally, in some rare inherited disorders, the formation of aortic aneurysms (and dissections) is linked to mutant forms of the TGF-βR associated with exuberant TGF-β signaling. Thus, antagonists of the TGF-β pathway like losartan may help patients with such disorders as well. As a result, drugs that fortuitously target TGF-β such as losartan are currently being evaluated in clinical trials.

Vitamin D: Lighting the Way Beyond Calcium Homeostasis

The major function of vitamin D is to facilitate the absorption and metabolism of calcium to support activities such as neuromuscular transmission and bone mineralization. Thus, the minimum daily requirement of 200 to 400 international units (IU), corresponding to 5 to 10 μg, was established as the amount necessary to prevent rickets and osteomalacia. However, that amount may be insufficient to sustain the other important activities supported by vitamin D.

The major source (90%) of vitamin D in humans is the ultraviolet B–driven conversion of endogenously synthesized 7-dehydrocholesterol precursors to cholecalciferol (vitamin D3). This is an important factoid, because in northern latitudes or in dark-skinned persons (melanin blocks the relevant light wavelengths)—or in cloistered medical students, children with thick coats of sunscreen, or heavily veiled women—supplementary dietary needs may be greater. The metabolism of vitamin D involves the following steps:

• Vitamin D3 is hydroxylated to its 25-hydroxy form through the cytochrome P-450; this is subsequently converted by renal tubular cells to 1,25-dihydroxy-vitamin D3, the most active form. Further 24-hydroxylation inactivates the molecule.
• 1,25-Dihydroxy-vitamin D3 is essentially a steroid hormone; it acts by binding an intracellular nuclear vitamin D receptor (VDR), which then forms heterodimers with the retinoid X receptor (RXR). These vitamin D–VDR–RXR complexes bind to vitamin D response elements and drive protein transcription.
• 1,25-Dihydroxy-vitamin D3 also can bind plasma membrane vitamin D receptors that directly activate protein kinase C and open calcium channels.

Virtually all cells—not just those involved in calcium homeostasis—express VDR. Of interest, macrophages, keratinocytes, and various epithelia (breast, colon, and prostate) can synthesize 1,25-dihydroxy-vitamin D3. In macrophages, activation of Toll-like receptors increases the synthesis of both VDR and 1,25-dihydroxy-vitamin D3, inducing the production of antimicrobial peptides such as cathelicidins, thus improving innate immunity. In all, more than 200 additional genes are regulated by vitamin D—including those that modulate proliferation, apoptosis, and angiogenesis. Epidemiologic data quite persuasively demonstrate that low 1,25-hydroxy-vitamin D3 levels correlate with a 30% to 50% greater incidence of colon, prostate, and breast cancers. Of interest, the vitamin D–inactivating 24-hydroxylase enzyme (CYP24A1) often is overexpressed in tumor cells. As a result of multiple epidemiologic studies, there is a movement to increase the daily minimal supplementation of vitamin D to greater than 1000 IU, especially in the winter in northern latitudes. Moreover, drugs that target the 24-hydroxylase CYP24A1 show promise in the therapy of certain epithelial malignancies. Clearly, ultraviolet light exposure should be balanced by concerns regarding cutaneous malignancy, and oral dosing should not be overdone lest vitamin D toxicity (and hypercalcemia) result. Overall, however, these considerations give all of us an excuse to spend more time in the sun and perhaps provide a greater impetus for selected vitamin supplementation.

Biofilm: We’ve Been Slimed

Bacteria exist either as single-celled “planktonic” free-floating organisms or as biofilms—complex adherent multicellular communities in a self-produced exopolysaccharide matrix “slime.” Biofilms occur anywhere that liquids and solids meet; good examples are the slippery surface of a boulder in a stream and the grunge that accumulates in a waste pipe. Significantly, roughly 80% of all human infections—including wound infections, catheter infections, endocarditis, urinary tract infections, and infections of implanted devices—are caused by biofilms. The numbers translate into almost 100,000 biofilm-related deaths each year in the United States.

The cell-cell interactions of bacteria in biofilms are regulated by the microbial production of quorum-sensing proteins that bind to specific receptors and coordinate the subsequent communal behavior. Up to 15% of the microbial genome is differentially regulated in the free versus biofilm forms of the same microorganism (approximately half are activated and the other half repressed). As a consequence of these genetic differences, bacteria in biofilms are over 1000 times more resistant to antimicrobial agents than their planktonic counterparts. This is ascribed to a less permeable microenvironment (slime), decreased microbial growth rates with a small population of “persister” cells, and upregulation of stress responses, in addition to a more efficient transfer of antimicrobial resistance genes. Also noteworthy (and disquieting) is that bacteria cultures in hospital microbiology labs—forming the basis for standard antibiotic sensitivity analysis—are more akin to planktonic bacteria than they are to biofilm.

Clearly, a biofilm infection poses a significant problem. Not only is the microbe hunkered down in a difficult-to-penetrate slime, and has upregulated genes that allow it to resist antimicrobial eradication, but the host response is likely to be prolonged, with significant potential “innocent bystander” damage. At present, the time-honored approach is to remove whatever surface is harboring the biofilm, followed by aggressive antibiotic treatment. Although this is reasonable for a catheter-based infection, it is substantially more problematic for an implanted heart valve or orthopedic prosthesis.

Accordingly, although not yet widely utilized, effective disruption of bacterial biofilms is a more-than-worthy therapeutic goal. A number of new therapies are under active (and even frenzied) investigation in animal models:

• Silver-coating (silver has broad antimicrobial activity) or antibiotic impregnation of catheters is of some benefit in frustrating the initial colonization that precedes biofilm formation.
• Applied electric currents or ultrasound vibration approaches also augment antibiotic therapies by partially disrupting biofilm colonies, and by increasing bacterial membrane permeability.
• More sophisticated tactics involve antisense molecules that silence the bacterial genes that are upregulated in biofilms, or synthetic decoy molecules that interfere with the quorum-sensing apparatus.
• Perhaps most exciting is the possibility that bacteriophage viruses can be conscripted to the battle; besides being potent and selective bacterial adversaries, these agents can contribute to the normal regulation of biofilms by producing polysaccharidases that hydrolyze slime.

Statins: Not Just About Cholesterol Anymore

The liver controls plasma cholesterol levels through three interrelated mechanisms:

• Hepatocytes clear cholesterol-rich low-density lipoprotein (LDL) from the plasma through cell surface LDL receptors, which release cholesterol into the cytoplasm.
• Intracellular cholesterol in turn negatively regulates the activity of steroid regulatory element–binding protein-1 (SREBP-1), a cholesterol-sensitive transcription factor that normally enhances the expression of LDL receptors and the enzyme 3-hydroxymethyl-3-glutaryl (HMG)-CoA (HMG-CoA) reductase.
• HMG-CoA reductase carries out the rate-limiting step in cholesterol synthesis; thus, when intracellular cholesterol levels fall, SREBP-1 drives the synthesis of HMG-CoA reductase, and cholesterol synthesis rises.

Statins belong to a widely used class of drugs that reduce cholesterol synthesis by inhibiting HMG-CoA reductase. Through the feedback loops just outlined, this increases the activity of SREBP-1 and the synthesis of LDL receptors, leading to increased clearance of LDL cholesterol from the plasma. Statins typically yield 10% to 50% reduction in plasma LDL. This translates into up to 60% reduction in cardiac events and 20% reduction in stroke in persons deemed to be at risk due to elevated levels of LDL cholesterol.

Of note, however, the cardiovascular benefits of statins consistently exceed the benefits anticipated on the basis of the extent of cholesterol lowering. For example, hypercholesterolemia has no statistically significant association with stroke, yet clinical studies have consistently shown that statin treatment reduces the incidence of stroke. Moreover, recent studies showed that stains reduce the incidence of clinically significant cardiovascular disease even in individuals with normal or very low cholesterols levels.

The foregoing observations suggest that protective mechanisms other than cholesterol reduction are afoot. As it turns out, HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors also block the formation of lipid precursors involved in the prenylation of a number of important intracellular proteins. Thus, the functions of both Ras (a key signaling molecule) and Rab (a regulator of membrane protein transport) depend on prenylation, which promotes the membrane association of these proteins. Through these and other less well-characterized “off-cholesterol” mechanisms, statins have a number of beneficial effects, including increased expression of the transcription factor KLF-2, which has anti-inflammatory effects in T cells and endothelial cells. Based on the important role in inflammation in atherosclerosis, it is easy to imagine how these effects of statins could contribute to a lowering of risk for cardiovascular events.

Statin therapy is not without side effects: A low incidence of rhabdomyolysis (severe autocatabolism of skeletal muscle) has been reported, along with hepatic metabolic derangements. These effects also are independent of its cholesterol-lowering activities and may be related to the activation of ubiquitin and proteasome degradation pathways.

Peripartum Cardiomyopathy: Proscribing Prolactin Promotes Promise

Pregnancy can be problematic in so many ways. Beyond deep vein thromboses, molar pregnancies, eclampsia, and amniotic fluid embolization, peripartum cardiomyopathy (PPCM) occurs with a frequency of roughly 1 in 3000 full-term gestations (higher in some ethnic groups); the outcome can be a severely dilated ventricle with a markedly diminished ejection fraction and congestive heart failure. Treating the heart failure of PPCM during pregnancy is tricky because many of the standard mainstays—warfarin (to minimize secondary thromboses) and angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors or receptor blockers (for afterload reduction)—are teratogenic. Although a majority of women eventually recover normal left ventricular function, a third or more experience a permanent deficit; there is also an overall 5% to 15% mortality rate, with another 5% to 10% of the patients eventually requiring cardiac transplantation.

The pathophysiology of PPCM remains something of a mystery, so prevention and definitive treatment are still evolving:

• During pregnancy, left ventricular myocardium normally undergoes reversible hypertrophy to accommodate physiologic increases in blood volume and cardiac output; in some cases, this is postulated to drive decompensation of a previously injured and marginally compensated heart. Delivery of the fetus should be followed by complete recovery in the vast majority of such cases—but this does not always occur.
• Viral myocarditis also can occur during or after pregnancy and can be worse with the relative immunosuppression accompanying gestation. This pathomechanism probably underlies a minority of cases, however, and steroid trials have not shown broad efficacy.
• Another theory holds that immune responses to circulating fetal cells that insinuate themselves into maternal myocardium (chimerism) are responsible. Unfortunately, therapy with intravenous immune globulin (to dampen immune responses) or pentoxifylline (to attenuate cytokine production) generally has not proved effective.

Enter new data and a therapeutic target. Prolactin is a pituitary hormone that is markedly upregulated after delivery; it is the hormone responsible for inducing lactation and uterine remodeling. In addition to a number of other properties, the full-length 23-kD protein also protects endothelial cells and promotes angiogenesis. Of note, however, a proteolytically cleaved 16-kD fragment of prolactin has precisely the opposite set of effects, causing endothelial cell apoptosis and disrupting capillary vasculature. Indeed, in animal models, increased production of the 16-kD peptide led to a pronounced dilated cardiomyopathy. Bringing the story full circle, increased oxidative stresses seen in PPCM patients are associated with increased proteolysis of the prolactin precursor and elevated circulating levels of the 16-kD molecule.

All of the foregoing suggests that blocking prolactin degradation or reducing its production can ameliorate PPCM. Fortunately, there is already a relatively safe drug on the market that does the latter: Bromocryptine is a dopamine agonist used to reduce prolactin synthesis in the setting of pituitary tumors that cause hyperprolactinemia. Even better, in recent clinical trials in women with PPCM, left ventricular functional recovery was significantly improved with bromocryptine treatment over that with standard heart failure therapy. Although suppression of lactation is a downside to the therapy (with potential physiologic and psychological ramifications), preventing permanent heart failure due to PPCM may be more than a tolerable trade-off.

Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor (TKI) Therapy: A Technical Knockout (TKO) for Myeloproliferative Disorders

Mutated, hyperactive tyrosine kinases underlie tumor cell growth and survival in myeloproliferative disorders (MPDs). Recognition of that paradigm has spurred the development of therapeutic agents that can selectively inhibit these rogue enzymes. As a class, these tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs) offer promise as agents that can reign in unfettered cellular proliferation while leaving normal cellular turnover virtually untouched. The best-known, imatinib, is now the mainstay of therapy for patients with chronic myeloid leukemia (CML).

CML is caused by constitutively active tyrosine signaling. This arises as a consequence of the balanced (9;22) chromosomal translocation that forms the Philadelphia chromosome—fusing genetic fragments from the BCR locus and the ABL oncogene. Basic research spawned by that fundamental cytogenetic observation led to the deciphering of the structure of the BCR-ABL fusion gene and the detection of the kinase activity of the BCR-ABL protein. Subsequent demonstration that BCR-ABL causes leukemia when expressed in the bone marrow cells of mice identified a possible therapeutic bull’s-eye; the screening of small molecule inhibitors of the unbridled BCR-ABL tyrosine kinase led to the discovery of imatinib, a first generation TKI that revolutionized the treatment of CML. As a bit of serendipity, in addition to inhibiting the BCR-ABL fusion protein, imatinib also blocks other tyrosine kinases such as platelet-derived growth factor receptor-α (PDGFRα), PDGFRβ, and KIT. As a consequence, it also is effective in treating certain other rare MPDs and gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) associated with activating mutations in those kinase proteins.

The success of TKI therapy for CML forged a new paradigm—and raised hopes—for developing specifically targeted cancer therapies and stimulated new efforts to use TKIs to treat a variety of hematologic malignancies. For example, TKIs have also proven to be effective when combined with conventional chemotherapy in improving outcomes in the subset of acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) that is associated with the presence of a BCR-ABL fusion gene, and clinical trials of JAK2 and FLT3 kinase inhibitors are currently under way in patients with primary myelofibrosis and refractory forms of acute myeloid leukemia, respectively.

Of course, there’s also a cautionary note. TKI therapy alone fails to completely eliminate CML in the vast majority of patients because the CML stem cells appears to be intrinsically resistant to TKIs, and so patients need to remain on therapy indefinitely. Furthermore, because of their inherent genomic instability, CML and other cancers driven by active tyrosine kinases sometimes develop resistance to TKIs, often because of the outgrowth of a tumor subclone with a mutation that prevents binding of TKI to its target tyrosine kinase. Fortunately, medical science is ahead of the game: The new mutations are somewhat predictable, and second-generation TKIs that are active against tyrosine kinases with mutations the produce resistance to imatinib are available (i.e., dasatinib and nilotinib).

Non–Small Cell Lung Cancer: Pathologic Details Can Beat the Devil

Non–small cell lung cancers (NSCLCs) constitute a group of epithelial malignancies that are pathologically and clinically distinct from the neuroendocrine-derived small cell lung carcinomas. Although histologically disparate from one another—they include squamous cell carcinomas, adenocarcinomas (comprising 50% of NSCLCs), and poorly differentiated large cell carcinomas—these tumors all share the depressing characteristic of responding poorly to standard cytotoxic chemotherapy. Indeed, failure to control NSCLC by surgical resection is associated with a miserable prognosis. The 5-year survival rate with even limited (less than 3 cm), localized stage I disease is only 50%; in the presence of distant metastases, less than 1% of patients survive to 5 years.

The picture is brightening, however, with the recognition that subsets of NSCLCs carry specific oncogenic mutations in potentially targetable molecules.

• Roughly 10% of adenocarcinomas in non-Asian persons (and roughly 50% of adenocarcinomas in Asian populations!) express constitutively activating mutations in epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR). EGFR is upstream of the mitogen-activated protein (MAP) kinase, Akt, and Janus kinase pathways, and activation leads to augmented cell proliferation. Of interest, in whites, these activating mutations tend to occur in adenocarcinomas arising in female patients who have never smoked; thus, the epidemiology strongly suggests a pathogenesis for such tumors distinct from that for other, smoking-related lung cancers. Moreover, EGFR mutant status strongly predicts improved progression-free survival with the administration of receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors such as gefitinib or erlotinib.
• Another, nonoverlapping subset of adenocarcinomas (roughly 5%) have acquired a mutant fusion protein (EML-ALK) that combines portions of the echinoderm microtubule-associated protein-like 4 (EML4) and anaplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK) molecules. The resultant chimeric protein is a constitutively activated kinase that drives cellular proliferation along MAP kinase pathways. Of importance, the kinase inhibitor crizotinib significantly improves patient survival when tumors contain the EML-ALK fusion protein.

Consequently, a better appreciation for the molecular underpinnings of NSCLC potentially allows exquisitely targeted therapy. To take advantage of such Achilles’ heels, however, current state-of-the-art pathologic diagnosis mandates careful ancillary evaluation in any new case. If the pathologist can identify mutant EGFR (by sequencing of tumor DNA), increased EGFR expression (by immunohistochemical analysis), or EML-ALK fusion rearrangement (by fluorescence in situ hybridization [FISH]), the oncologist has some improved and more selective weapons to bring to bear.

Polycystic Kidney Disease: A Failure to Communicate

Autosomal dominant adult polycystic kidney disease (ADPKD) affects 0.1% to 0.4% of the population and underlies 5% to 10% of all cases of end-stage renal disease. At present, the therapeutic options for patients with end-stage disease are the same as for patients with other kidney diseases: either chronic dialysis or transplantation.

ADPKD results from mutations in PKD1 and PKD2, genes that code for the polycystin-1 and -2 proteins, respectively.

• Polycystin-1 and -2 are expressed by the epithelial cells of the distal nephron and the collecting ducts, as well as by bile duct epithelium and endothelial cells (possibly explaining the hepatic cysts and vascular aneurysms that also occur in ADPKD).
• Polycystin-1 (PC-1) is part of the multi-subunit primary cilium, a nonmotile hairlike organelle that projects from the apical face of the epithelium and senses mechanical forces such as shear generated by fluid movements. When stimulated, the primary cilium triggers a series of events that increase cytoplasmic calcium.
• Polycystin-2 (PC-2) is a calcium channel; it is another component of the primary cilium complex and also is found in the endoplasmic reticulum. PC-2 regulates the uptake of calcium from the extracellular milieu and from intracellular stores in the endoplasmic reticulum.

In general, the mutations responsible for ADPKD decrease PC-1 or PC-2 function, resulting in abnormally low intracellular calcium levels. This effect has several consequences, but among the most important is a higher level of intracellular cyclic AMP (cAMP), which stimulates epithelial proliferation and activates the cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR), leading to increased fluid secretion. Tubular epithelium proliferation and increased fluid secretion underlies the formation of cysts, which eventually replace the normal parenchyma.

Fortunately, this pathogenic pathway also suggests therapeutic opportunities. Current attention is focused on modulating intracellular cAMP levels through blockade of the vasopressin pathway. Vasopressin (also known as antidiuretic hormone) binds to the V2 receptor and promotes water absorption in the collecting duct epithelium by stimulating adenyl cyclase—the enzyme that catalyzes the formation of cAMP. Selective V2 receptor antagonists such as tolvaptan decrease intracellular cAMP and reduce proliferation and fluid secretion, while avoiding complications related to antagonism of V1 receptors (which regulate heart rate and blood pressure). V2 antagonists are now in phase three clinical trials; it is hoped that these agents will slow or prevent the currently inexorable progression of ADPKD.

Aspirin and NSAIDs: Relief More Than Pain

Years of epidemiologic and interventional study have convincingly demonstrated that routine use of aspirin or other cyclooxygenase (COX) inhibitors reduces the risk of developing colorectal carcinoma in the general population. In patients with familial adenomatous polyposis, who have a markedly increased risk of colon cancer due to APC mutations, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) objectively reduce the size and number of existing polyps, thereby mediating primary colon cancer chemoprevention. In murine models involving human gene—like APC mutations, concurrent COX-1 or COX-2 deficiency reduces the incidence of malignancy by 80%. NSAIDs also have been shown to decrease cancer-specific mortality after diagnosis, particularly for patients with tumors that overexpress the COX-2 isoform (90% of colorectal cancers). This finding suggests that beyond inducing colon cancers, COX activity (or some other effect mitigated by NSAIDs) also promotes tumor progression.

Many of the chemopreventive and chemotherapeutic effects of NSAIDs are attributable to direct COX inhibition. This makes sense in light of the fact that the COX-driven generation of prostaglandin E2 and thromboxane A2 can be tumorigenic, because these pro-inflammatory mediators also can influence epithelial proliferation, angiogenesis, and metastatic potential. Thus, it’s hardly surprising that the irreversible nonselective COX inhibitor aspirin, as well as the selective and reversible COX-2 inhibitors (e.g., celecoxib), provides therapeutic efficacy. Administration of ω3-polyunsaturated fatty acids (eicosapentaenoic acid), which are metabolized by COX to anti-inflammatory resolvins (at the expense of fewer pro-inflammatory metabolites), also is beneficial.

On the other hand, some of the NSAID benefits appear to be COX-independent. Celecoxib analogues or sulfone metabolites of sulindac that do not inhibit COX-1 or -2 also are effective in preventing tumors in mouse models. Thus, aspirin—and to a lesser extent the other NSAIDs—can inhibit NFκB activation, promote β-catenin degradation, and downregulate survivin, all leading to the apoptosis of neoplastic cells. Although these actions of aspirin and NSAIDs provide plausible explanation of their antineoplastic activity, they also raise the question of why this efficacy is restricted to colonic tumors.

Regardless of the actual mechanisms involved, it is only slightly ironic that such an old (and inexpensive) drug like aspirin can have such a salubrious payoff. Certainly in the setting of previous malignancy or existing high-risk APC mutations, the small risk of gastrointestinal hemorrhage from aspirin is far outweighed by the benefits. Moreover, if the true beneficial pathways can be elucidated, a drug lacking the existing NSAID side effects can’t be far behind.

Hep to Go: Beyond Ribavirin and Interferon for Hepatitis C

Hepatitis C (“hep C”) infections result in chronic disease in more than 80% of affected persons, of whom 20% to 30% experience progression to cirrhosis. Consequently, hepatitis C is the most common cause of chronic liver disease in the United States and is the number-one indication for liver transplantation. Even worse, 5% of chronically infected patients develop hepatocellular carcinoma.

At the time of the initial infection with hepatitis C virus (HCV), most patients do not mount a sufficiently robust initial immune response to clear the RNA virus, and with a low-fidelity viral polymerase, HCV acquires new mutations at a prodigious rate. Moreover, HCV makes a protease that can cleave adaptor molecules, and its core protein inhibits intracellular kinase signaling, both of which normally drive an antiviral response.

Preventing the initial infection is clearly the best way to avoid the sequelae, but the search for a vaccine has been impeded by poorly immunogenic envelope proteins and a heterogeneous mixture of viral subspecies with minimal antigenic overlap. Accordingly, the current clinical approach focuses on frustrating viral replication and augmenting the host innate response:

• Ribavirin is a nucleoside analogue that the viral polymerase incorporates into the viral genome, thereby promoting “lethal” mutagenesis; it can pair with cytidine and uridine (mimicking guanine and adenine bases), leading to a theoretical “error catastrophe.” Ribavirin also can inhibit cellular inosine monophosphate dehydrogenase, resulting in guanosine triphosphate (GTP) depletion and inhibition of viral replication.
• Interferon-α is a cytokine that drives a number of innate immune responses that assist in viral eradication by improved natural killer cell activity and by inhibition of HCV replication.

Unfortunately, the standard two-drug cocktail is expensive ($20,000 for the typical 48-week course) and has many untoward side effects such as cytopenias, fatigue, and depression. In addition, it is effective in only about 40% of patients. Much effort, therefore, is being devoted to the development of next-generation therapies such as protease inhibitors. These therapies are based on the current understanding of the molecular basis of viral replication.

After infection, the HCV genome initially is translated as a single long polyprotein that has to be cleaved by a specific viral serine protease (NS3) for virus assembly to occur. Consequently, use of selective protease inhibitors constitutes an attractive form of adjunctive therapy. Indeed, when added to interferon and ribavirin, protease inhibitors such as telaprevir and boceprevir greatly reduce viral replication in almost 70% of cases, and in many patients, HCV is undetectable within 12 to 24 weeks. Such triple-compound regimens are likely to become the standard of care within a short period of time; moreover, in a fashion analogous to that for the highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection, triple-drug cocktails also may squelch HCV infections—from so many different directions—that they never get the chance to mutate.

Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia: Bigger Is Not Necessarily Better

Like death and taxes, progressive prostatic enlargement is a near certainty in aging males (and not just humans—older male rats, rabbits, and dogs also are susceptible). Affecting 20% of men by age 40, the incidence of so-called benign prostatic hypertrophy (BPH) rises to 70% by age 60 and surpasses 90% by age 80. Moderate to severe symptoms occur in roughly a third of those so afflicted, resulting from compression of the prostatic urethra by the enlarged prostate. Patients classically experience urinary frequency, nocturia, difficulty in starting or stopping the urinary stream, and dysuria and are at a greater risk for urinary tract infections. In some cases, the presenting manifestation is acute urinary retention.

The key molecule in the pathogenesis of BPH is 5α-reductase (5AR) type 2. It converts circulating testosterone to dihydrotestosterone (DHT). DHT, in turn, forms a tight complex with nuclear androgen receptors within stromal and epithelial cells, driving the elaboration of a host of growth factors and their receptors. This results in proliferation of stromal as well as glandular cells and inhibition of apoptosis. The problem posed by prostatic enlargement is compounded by an increase in smooth muscle tone in the prostate stroma, urethra, and bladder neck.

BPH is treated by surgical and medical therapies:

• Transurethral resection of the prostate (TURP) or updated variations on that theme (using lasers, microwaves, radiofrequency energy, or high-intensity ultrasound) remain the surgical gold standard. These modalities work by physically removing or otherwise ablating tissue adjacent to the urethra.
• Because of the increased smooth muscle tone, drugs that relax smooth muscle contraction, such as α-adrenergic receptor antagonists, also are beneficial. Agents that act selectively on the α1A receptor (expressed in the prostate, urethra, and bladder, but not elsewhere), such as tamsulosin, improve urinary flow by relaxing the smooth muscles, with minimal side effects.

Several, more elegant approaches to treating BPH are currently available. One involves blocking the production of DHT with inhibitors of 5AR such as finasteride and dutasteride. Without DHT, the prostatic stroma and epithelium lose their proliferative signals and even involute as antiapoptotic signals are removed. As an extra benefit, some 5AR inhibitors that block the type 1 enzyme (found in skin and liver) also can be effective for the treatment of alopecia (hair loss)—truly an example of better living through chemistry! A second approach involves the use of phosphodiesterase-5 inhibitors such as Tadalafil, which also relaxes smooth muscle by increasing cyclic GMP levels. As an added benefit, it also is an effective treatment for erectile dysfunction, potentially permitting two problems of male aging to be treated with a single pill.

HER2 Now: Targeted Therapy for Breast Cancer

Breast cancer is the most common malignancy in women, with a lifetime risk of roughly one in eight. It is second only to lung cancer as a cause of female cancer deaths. However, breast cancer is not a monolithic disease; survival statistics (and potential therapies) are associated with different tumor characteristics, including estrogen and progesterone hormone receptor status, gene expression profiles, and certain mutations. In particular, amplification of the HER2 gene leading to overexpression of the HER2 protein (also called Her2/neu or c-ErbB-2) occurs in 20% to 30% of invasive breast cancers and is associated with a poor prognosis. Fortunately, HER2 overexpression also provides a target for an effective therapy.

HER2 is one of four related transmembrane epidermal growth factor receptors with intrinsic tyrosine kinase activity. When these receptors form homo- or heterodimers after ligand binding, downstream kinase signaling promotes proliferation through a MAP kinase pathway and blocks apoptosis through AKT-dependent mechanisms. Significantly, the extracellular portion of HER2 can dimerize in the absence of ligand. Consequently, overexpression of HER2 can lead to unabated kinase activity through autodimerization.

HER2 overexpression is usually demonstrated by immunohistochemical staining showing increased membrane protein expression and is confirmed by fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) showing extra copies of the gene. Of interest, although HER2 overexpression occurs with some frequency in breast cancer, it is only rarely seen in other malignancies.

Recognition of HER2 overexpression in a subset of breast cancers led to the development of a monoclonal antibody, trastuzumab, that inhibits HER2 signaling. Trastuzumab also may promote Her2 internalization and degradation, or kill tumors through antibody-dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity. If there is no Her2 overexpression, the monoclonal antibody provides no benefit. Regardless of the mechanism, patients receiving a course of the monoclonal antibody in addition to standard chemotherapies show almost 50% better response rates, with significantly improved disease-free and overall survival. Indeed, trastuzumab was the first monoclonal antibody to prolong life for patients with epithelial malignancies.

Cardiotoxicity is the only significant side effect, developing in about 4% of patients; it is attributable to the role that HER2 signaling apparently plays in myocardial damage repair. The one other limitation of trastuzumab is that it does not cross the blood-brain barrier; the central nervous system thus becomes a sanctuary for metastatic disease. It is hoped that, small molecule inhibitors of HER2 that penetrate the CNS will alleviate this vexing problem and are currently being evaluated in clinical trials.

Block of AGEs: Unlinking Glucose from Diabetic Complications

Roughly a third of diabetic patients will suffer significant cardiovascular complications within 5 to 10 years of their initial diagnosis. Ischemic heart disease, stroke, and peripheral vascular disease not only are major contributors to the morbidity and mortality associated with chronically elevated blood glucose but also account for the lion’s share of the clinical costs.

Some of the pathology is attributable to intracellular mayhem. Thus, in cells like neurons and those of the endothelium, where insulin is not required to drive glucose transport, extracellular hyperglycemia causes intracellular hyperglycemia through mass action. Subsequent enzymatic reduction of the elevated intracellular glucose load causes a hyperosmolar state and—by consuming NADPH—a severe oxidative stress. Intracellular hyperglycemia also activates protein kinase C, leading to the production of profibrotic and proangiogenic cytokines.

The other major consequence of hyperglycemia is nonenzymatic glycation of intra- and extracellular proteins to generate an irreversibly modified advanced glycation end-product (AGE). By binding to specific vascular wall and inflammatory cell receptors, AGEs are potently procoagulant and pro-inflammatory. The glycation chemistry also causes protein cross-linking that reduces matrix turnover and traps molecules in the interstitium (e.g., proatherogenic low-density lipoproteins).

In view of the cellular and chemical effects of hyperglycemia, it is easy to see how the cardiovascular system takes a beating. Both large and small vessels are overall more prone to thrombosis and also to the development of accelerated atherosclerosis; in addition, protein cross-linking (with increased matrix synthesis) engenders changes that result in a stiffened and noncompliant vasculature. Such effects in the coronary circulation render the heart relatively ischemic, and cross-linking of myocardial collagen adversely affects both systolic contraction and diastolic relaxation.

The current major therapeutic approach to diabetes focuses on reducing circulating glucose levels, either by improving insulin production or insulin responsiveness or—failing those—by administering exogenous insulin. Although this may control ongoing glycemia, patients are left with the accumulated backlog of AGEs and cross-linked proteins—which are slow to degrade and a cause of persistent cellular dysfunction.

Thus, there is substantial enthusiasm for a new class of small-molecule cross-link“breakers” (e.g., aminoguanidine, alagebrium); these can chemically interact with carbonyl intermediates to prevent formation of irreversibly cross-linked adducts. As it turns out, these agents also chelate divalent cations that contribute to cellular oxidation reactions and are potent scavengers of oxidizing sugars and free radicals. By whatever mechanism, in both animal models and early human trials, a number of these molecules have been shown to improve arterial compliance, endothelial function, diastolic relaxation, and myocardial contractility. Although they may not be able to reverse severe end-stage vascular damage, AGE breakers hold substantial promise as agents for adjunctive therapy to limit the long-term cardiovascular complications of glycation-associated cross-linking.

Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy: When Less Is Maybe More

Duchenne muscular dystrophy (DMD) is a recessive X-linked form of striated muscle degeneration affecting roughly 1 in 3500 boys. It has an unremitting course and carries a dismal prognosis, typically with wheelchair dependency by age 12 and death by age 25 due to cardiomyopathy and respiratory complications. The fundamental defect is a mutation in the dystrophin gene that encodes a large structural protein with 79 exons. Frameshift or early-termination mutations in DMD lead to the total absence of functional dystrophin; lack of the dystrophin gives rise to a series of bimolecular changes that culminate in myocyte cell death.

Current treatment involves physical therapy and use of orthopedic appliances (e.g., braces) to maintain skeletal function for as long as possible. Anabolic corticosteroids can be a temporizing measure: They increase sarcomeric synthesis and efficiency of contraction. Eventually, however, myofiber loss supervenes. Likewise, β2-agonists increase muscle contraction and hence strength but do not affect disease progression.

Whereas total lack of dystrophin leads to DMD, the milder Becker muscular dystrophy (BMD) results from mutations that allow variable expression of smaller truncated dystrophin proteins. These mutations cause a loss of one or more exons. Thus, in BMD, a later onset of muscle changes is characteristic, with a more slowly progressive clinical disease. Recognition of this important difference between the two muscular dystrophies pointed the way to a radical exon-skipping therapeutic approach to treatment in which DMD is essentially converted to a form of BMD.

By identifying the relevant mutation in each case of DMD, site-specific antisense oligonucleotides (AONs) can be generated that induce the transcriptional apparatus to “leapfrog” over the defective exon, effectively splicing out the offending sequence. Although the resulting dystrophin is smaller than the full-length protein, it may retain much of its normal function. Remarkably, one such agent, an AON that results in skipping of exon 51, has recently been approved for treatment of of patients with certain DMD mutations. It is hoped that chronic treatment with such agents will convert DMD from an inevitably fatal disease to a chronic disease associated with an improved and prolonged quality of life.

Plaque Attack: Untangling Alzheimer Disease

Alzheimer disease (AD) is the most common cause of dementia, characterized as cognitive decline and short-term memory loss; it is also the sixth most common cause of death in the United States. With more definitive, life-prolonging treatments for cardiovascular and neoplastic disease, in combination with the general aging of the population, the incidence of AD can be expected to increase dramatically in the coming decades. For the United States, this is projected at 1 million additional patients each year, with approximately 15 million afflicted persons by 2050. Clearly, the coming deluge of dementia provides a strong impetus to develop improved therapies; even better would be to check AD in its very earliest stages.

Current first-line therapies are intended to ameliorate the progressive cognitive decline of AD. Because memory is regulated through cholinergic pathways, cholinesterase inhibitors (e.g., donepezil, rivastigmine) are prescribed to increase acetylcholine levels. In addition, because glutamate influences long-term potentiation—important for learning and memory—another class of drugs (e.g., memantine) that block N-methyl-d-aspartase (NMDA) receptors, which regulate glutamate levels, has emerged. Unfortunately, these drugs provide at best only modest gains (1% to 5% improvement on various AD assessment scales), with side effects that adversely affect up to half of the patients. Moreover, cholinesterase inhibitors and NMDA antagonists only treat the symptoms and do not attack the underlying causes. With time, ongoing neuronal injury soon overtakes any transient pharmacologic benefit.

By comparison, drugs in the pipeline target putative AD pathogenic pathways. The prevailing view is that a transmembrane amyloid precursor protein (APP) is sequentially processed by β-(extracellular) and γ- (intramembranous) proteases called secretases. These generate a 42-amino-acid peptide (Aβ) that forms toxic oligomers, or misfolds into insoluble amyloid plaque. Of note, an alternate pathway involving sequential α- and γ-secretase cleavages does not result in the pathologic Aβ peptide. Besides direct neurotoxicity, Aβ complexes also induce increased phosphorylation of intracellular tau, a protein that stabilizes neuronal microtubules; hyperphosphorylated tau then aggregates into cytoplasmic neurofibrillary tangles, and the microtubule architecture collapses.

In light of the central role envisaged for Aβ, β- and γ-secretase inhibitors and α-secretase stimulators are all reasonable targets. Indeed, β-secretase inhibitors (e.g., thiazolidinediones) improve AD scores but may be of limited value because neuregulin-1 (involved in myelination) is a normal β-secretase substrate. Unfortunately, γ-secretase inhibitors have failed in clinical trials, possibly again in part because of inhibitory effects on Notch receptors, which also are γ-secretase substrates. Other approaches have been designed to inhibit Aβ aggregation (e.g., tramiprosate) or harness the immune system to engulf and degrade plaques and oligomers; anti-Aβ monoclonal antibodies such as bapineuzumab and solanezumab may accomplish this. Finally, inhibition of tau phosphorylation (NP-03112) or aggregations are viable strategies currently in clinical trials.

Thus, although AD is still a depressingly progressive and still largely intractable disorder, the foregoing advances in the fundamental understanding of its pathogenesis have provided several encouraging strategies for attacking the plaques.

Melanoma: Bright Hopes for a Dark Tumor

Metastatic melanoma is a lethal disease. If a lesion cannot be recognized at a stage at which primary resection is adequate for control, the median survival is 7 months—even less if more than a single metastasis is present. As a consequence, melanoma is responsible for greater than three quarters of the mortality associated with skin cancers, amounting to roughly 9000 deaths annually in the United States and 48,000 worldwide. A distressing reality is that even small and apparently completely excised lesions also can harbor occult metastases at the time of original resection; in the absence of good adjuvant prophylaxis, late recurrence is always a concern.

Fortunately, the armamentarium available to fight back is growing, using a combination of augmented immunity and new chemotherapeutic agents that disrupt molecular pathways involved in proliferation of melanomas.

In the former category, topical imiquimod at the site of primary excision can activate cutaneous immune cells via Toll-like receptor 7, leading to local elaboration of a variety of pro-inflammatory cytokines. Systemically, immunomodulation is accomplished through interferon or interleukin-2 therapies, although these have been effective in only a small subset of patients. More encouraging, the introduction of ipilimumab—anti-CTLA-4 (cytotoxic T lymphocyte—associated antigen 4) monoclonal antibodies—has improved survival in metastatic melanoma by 20%, putatively by blocking the negative regulation of cytotoxic T cells through this surface receptor. Unfortunately, not only do these therapies have significant adverse side effects, but they can be very expensive and only rarely effect a cure.

Recent advances have greatly improved current understanding of the mutations that drive melanoma growth. These have been instrumental in developing targeted therapies. Melanoma cells seem to be “addicted”to MAPK (mitogen-activated protein kinase) pathways for growth, maintenance, drug resistance, and progression. Indeed, 40% to 60% of melanomas (and 7% to 8% of all cancers) carry activating mutations in the B-Raf serine-threonine protein kinase that is a component of the MAPK signaling; a remarkable 90% of these mutations involve a specific substitution of glutamic acid for valine at amino acid 600 (V600E). The high prevalence of B-Raf V600E in melanomas has allowed the development of kinase inhibitors specific for the mutant enzyme. In trials of two such inhibitors, vemurafenib and dabrafenib, complete or partial regression was observed in the vast majority of tumors carrying the mutated B-Raf, with almost double the duration of progression-free survival.

Still, this improvement does not equal a cure, and tumors eventually develop resistance through secondary N-Ras mutations, upregulation of other surface receptor tyrosine kinases, or B-Raf truncations. The success of these approaches, however, points to an eventually much brighter prognosis for such a dark malignancy.